hello I'm your host David Barnard and my
guest today is Asia palone VP of
strategy at wel Tre the most popular
all-in-one Wellness app on the app store
on the podcast I talk with Asia about
what to do when there are no jobs to be
done how to build Innovative features
and why copying dualingo engagement
strategy probably won't work for your
app hi AIA thanks so much for joining me
on the podcast today hi David thanks for
having me so I want to get started with
the story of Welter and you just told me
right before we started recording that
Welter is actually a combination of
wellness and laboratory which I think is
really cool and maybe is kind of a hint
at what the app does but yeah why don't
you tell us a story of the founding of
the app and then how you ended up
joining the team yeah sure so I think
Welter being Wellness laboratory isn't
just a hint about what the app does it's
also a hint about how it was founded so
basically my lovely founder Jane she was
and is a Serial entrepreneur and aside
from being a Serial entrepreneur she
also had mentored a bunch of startups
and at some point she noticed a that she
was suffering from burnout and B that a
lot of the startups she was mentoring
were failing not because the idea was
bad or that the people were incompetent
or that nobody needed the product it's
because like as a Founder once you hit
too many bumps in the road you just burn
out you're just done and then you just
you can't rise up up to the next
challenge and she became very interested
in the mechanics of how it works cuz you
know like a lot of people who work
really hard they neglect their bodies
and it comes back to haunt them the
original idea was to solve this problem
was to create a health app basically
that could help people prevent burnout
so they could live their lives do
whatever they want and keep going in
spite of all the challenges that we face
and the original idea was literally to
have like a person service run by humans
who would collect people's data from all
their Fitness gadgets and trackers and
stuff like this and then try to analyze
it so you would pay for a service where
you have like a personal analyst who
goes through your data and is like okay
when you sleep less your productivity
goes down or when you go for a run like
it helps you I don't know increase your
heart rate variability just stuff like
that but of course stuff like this is
difficult to scale but it was originally
like a wellness laboratory literally
there were people analyzing people's
data and telling them what they need to
feel better Jane realized that the
metric that most accurately reflected
people's well-being and health was a
metric called heart rate variability I
think everyone now knows that this
metric exists it's in your Apple watch
it's in the Garment stuff like that but
back in 2016 it was not in any gadgets
yet and originally Welter was just an
app that measures heart rate variability
and analyzes it and ass super scientific
cool and personalized way and kind of
tells you how your body is doing I'm
super Innovative we have actually a
bunch of scientific Publications and
journals about how our algorithm is the
best it adapts the camera really well
and the app still does this actually and
then it turned so we pivoted to an app
and then I think there were a couple of
other pivots like at some point we tried
even having your own wearable and then
we pivoted towards a kind of a Google
analytics for health so there's like
this one metric that people use to
measure their overall well-being and
then they connect a whole bunch of other
data and basically look on a really
complicated dashboard to see which of
their lifestyle factors like how they
slept how much they walked and stuff
like this all impacted this one
important metric and this worked
beautifully for a very very Niche
audience yeah it's kind of the sometimes
a Founder trap right it's like you build
something for yourself and then you
realize like oh wait I'm the only person
and like 10 other people like me are the
only target market oh wait a minute we
need a bigger Tam for this to be
successful yeah so how did you expand
beyond that like really narrow niche of
people so this niche of people is like
it's not that narrow it's pretty big
it's like all the guys who listen to
Andrew hman you know
people uh people who want the kind of
like Google analytics for health are
very specific they're either like
athletes or they're internal optimizers
there's big cohorts of them but we kind
of realized that it's not going to work
for the mass audience because most of us
have no time during the day to do
absolutely anything for our health and
we're not going to look at complicated
dashboards and be like okay I need to
add 20 minutes to my sleep in order to
boost my productivity by I don't know
15% or something the next day so we kind
of started to try to figure out what it
is that people actually want want from
health and wellness apps and what jobs
they're trying to complete when they're
downloading and using these apps and we
came to a very interesting conclusion
which is that there are actually no jobs
to be done in health and wellness apps
and what I mean by that so if you look
at the overall health and wellness
Market you'll see that there's a lot of
Niche offers so there's things for
athletes because these are the people
who are already going on some kind of
run or doing a workout or something like
this and they just need an app to help
them like track their pacing and stuff
like this and then there's apps for
people who are really sick so people who
have blood pressure issues for example
they need a blood pressure Journal
because they have to measure their blood
pressure every day so for both of these
segments like people who are athletes or
optimizers and people who are sick
something happens to them every single
day that prompts them to open the app or
use the product and it kind of like
gives those those apps fairly High
retention rate but for most people
they're not going on runs every day
they're not taking care of their health
every day and there's no like real life
event you know when you have to call an
Uber something is happening to you in
real life you need to get to a place and
then you open this app to get the job
done that's a really interesting Framing
and as you were talking I was even
realizing some of the bigger apps in
health and wellness like one that stands
out very specifically is drava
and kind of in your framing it actually
makes a ton of sense that that app grew
as big as it did because there's a very
specific job to be done tracking your
cycling or there's kind of a main job to
be done and then there's all sorts of
sub jobs to be done as far as like
sharing it with friends and like
capturing the leaderboards and things
like that but there's that like trigger
and I think not enough apps go this deep
in understanding that so like if you're
struggling with retention if you're
struggling with growth it's probably
time to take a step back and like do
this kind of analysis but then once you
realize okay there's not these natural
triggers there's not these jobs to be
done in this kind of more broad Wellness
app how did you fix that where did you
go from there well I'll go on a side
note it's not necessarily something that
needs to be fixed for everyone sometimes
it's okay to just work for our niche
market and work for that niche market so
well that you completely win them over
and I think that's cool and really great
like I use a lot of products I keep
trying different like weightlifting apps
cuz I'm looking for the ideal one and if
someone makes me the ideal weightlifting
app I will be super happy so I don't
mean to say that everyone necessarily
needs to look at how do we win this
complicated like Mass Market game but
with weltering specifically we have a
more broad Mission which is to improve
people's well-being with science and
technology that serves each individual
personally and so when you put it that
way you kind kind of have to win over
the mass market so all of those people
who actually don't have any jobs that
need to be done in health and wellness
Tech so where we started thinking about
it we started looking for a trigger okay
there are no natural triggers that are
occurring people's lives that would
prompt them to open a health and
wellness app and be like okay tell me
what I need to do to take care of my
health right now but if you walk down
the street or if you just like watch
people go about their day you'll notice
there does a very odd trigger in
people's lives like you know when you
see someone standing in line and they're
kind of bored and to alleviate this
boredom they open their phone and they
start flipping through like Tik Tok or
Instagram or something like this I call
this trigger existential horror you
don't want to deal with living so you
kind of like you start opening stuff and
you start reading stuff and you're like
okay I'll just distract myself from the
horrifying thoughts that are like going
on in my brain so we thought okay the
only way that we can make make a health
and wellness app for the mass Market is
if we use this trigger and somehow
convince people that instead of opening
like Instagram or Tik Tok they can open
a health and wellness app and it would
be just as fun and just as entertaining
but also good for them so that was our I
guess final big pivot where we decided
that a wellness app must be extremely
entertaining it has to show people
something new every time they open the
app and it has to really avoid shaming
people because a lot of times people who
think about their ideal Health they're
like okay I will just give people very
specific metrics very specific goals
that they have to meet every day but
then of course what happens is people
open this app they haven't met any of
their goals their metrics look bad and
that's the last thing you want to see if
you're standing in line and you're
opening an app to distract yourself you
don't want the existential horror to get
worse right you
you want the existential horror to get
better so we embarked on this odd
journey of making a wellness app that
moves away from the goal setting and the
shaming and more towards the tick tock
and Instagram type of entertainment so
you've kind of hinted at it but I wanted
to actually read off this list because
you and I first met an MA in Vegas I was
actually in your session and then came
up to you after the session because I
just thought it was so great so in that
session and I went back to the slides
and took notes you listed five things I
actually wanted to go through each five
of these individually you kind of gave
the overview but your list that you gave
on stage is make it magical make it
relevant make sense in real time make it
novel make it pleasurable I just thought
that was such a great framework a great
list a great series of things to think
about and again kind of like you said
about if you're not a mass market app
you can serve a niche and not have to
think about all these sorts of things
but I think this is a fun list for
anybody to think through so let's think
through each of these individually like
what do you mean make it magical and
then how did that play out in Welter so
I came across the concept of magical
apps in a very odd way I was reading a
book about the witch trials by this
wonderful feminist scholar Sylvia
federici and she was talking about why
it was so important during the rise of
capitalism to break the power of Mag and
to eliminate witchcraft because in
essence magic at its core is the refusal
of work in action so when we think about
things that are magical there are things
that give people something for doing
absolutely nothing and preferably
something that's like very pretty and
sparkly and like looks nice and makes us
feel good so when we think about the
ideal health and wellness app I wanted
to have that Vibe you have to do nothing
and then you get things that make you
feel better and are also good for your
health that's kind of the vibe that
we're going for so what we do is for
example like we have a very intense
extremely scientific analysis of
people's heart rate variability and we
could present this analysis in any way
that we like I guess we could give
people charts like cool metrics and
stuff like that but instead of doing all
of this what we did as we packed it into
a really cool visualization of like this
liquid that changes color and behavior
depending on how your body is feeling
right now so say if someone is super
stressed it turns red and kind of starts
bubbling over almost like over the top
or if you have a lot of energy you just
woke up and you slept well and like you
and I today it'll probably it'll
probably be green and then if you're
really calm and ready to focus this is
my favorite color to get it turns into
like an ocean blue so this kind of thing
gives people something cool and pretty
to look at and they don't have to do
anything to get it because we pull their
heart rate variability data directly
from their Apple watch and we just turn
it into this magical thing it's our core
feature and people really love it and I
think the reason people love it is that
they're doing nothing and they're
getting this like magical surprising new
thing every time they open the app that
is so cool all right make it relevant
what do you mean we let our users
connect over a thousand different data
sources because people care about
different things and the idea here was
to try to tie people's Wellness Matrix
to things that they actually care about
so for example if you're a developer you
can like connect your number of GitHub
commits to Welter we have this algorithm
that scans people's data all the time
for scientific data correlations and
then to try to like motivate this person
in a very personalized way we'll send
them a correlation that says hey when
you run in the evenings your GitHub
commits the next day go up so when
you're telling people something that is
very personalized you're not telling
them okay if you're like super stressed
today eventually if you're stressed over
and over for long periods of time your
risk of a heart attack might increase 10
years down the line they'll be like okay
I'll worry about that 10 years down the
line but if it impacts something more
immediate like my relationships with
people my work my ability to pay my bill
people are a bit more likely to care so
the more personalized you can get with
your segments the better and you Curr of
already delved into it but the next one
is make sense in real time anything to
add there or is that kind of the gist of
it is like you need those relevant
moments in real time not just kind of
relevant to the Future so we recently
released a new feature at Welter it's
like a more static home screen that
shows people how well they're dealing
with the world's top killer set and AR
stress what I noticed when I was
researching a lot of home screens in
these health and wellness apps is that
they kind of give you a lot of data to
track your day so they'll be like okay
this is how your heart rate change this
is how many steps you walk this is how
many calories you burned but I don't
know what that really means for me like
what does it mean that my stress level
is 48% like I don't know what that means
so the idea here was to not just create
a home screen that visualizes people's
data for them but to create something
that makes sense of all of this data so
it's actually a home screen that reacts
to absolutely every single step you take
and every single heartbeat your watch
tracks and make sense of this date and
real time instead of just like
visualizing it in a raw format and then
how do you make all of that data novel
The principle of novelty I guess when I
talked about our final pivot this is
what we ended up doing with the app we
created something that showed people
something new every time they open the
app because it's like a basic mechanism
that exists in every single one of these
apps that help people cope with
existential horror like every time you
open Facebook or Tik Tok or Instagram
you see something new like it's a little
bit unexpected and that creates a
feeling of reward for people and that's
why they keep coming back to it so the
way we did it and please for the love of
God do not do this is before the
existence of generative AI we created
our very own janky generative AI it was
basically an infinite content generation
system that would change the text and
visuals that people saw depending on how
their data changed so we have I think
maybe like 45 different message types
and then every message types has like
nearly infinite amounts of content I
think if you took all of Welter content
together that we've been able to
generate it would cover like four
volumes of Lord of the Rings over this
was really difficult it aged me like 10
years I swear um so your stress scores
on Welter were terrible during that time
exactly but really that's what helped us
get that initial retention boost is that
people kept coming back to us because
they were seeing something new every
time they open the app people don't have
to do this now like we have a lot of
generative AI that can kind of help
developers do this without going through
the horror that we had to go through at
Walter I love that you're also by
thinking through these things kind of
taking the tools of the Tik toks and
Facebooks and Twitter's and turning them
on their head instead of being the
negative Doom scrolling you're kind of
feeding that dopamine and Novelty
seeking with actually like good for you
things it's taking the tools of these
negative feedback loops in our lives and
instead creating a positive feedback
loop which I think is really cool and
again like not all of these are going to
apply to every app but if there's
opportunity to use some of these
techniques in an app it does it
increases retention people enjoy and
actually that's the next one we're going
to get to but you want people to enjoy
opening your app they're going to open
it more so the last one is make it
pleasurable what does that mean so what
I mean by this is people like things
that make them feel good and they don't
like things that make them feel bad so
if your user is tired at the end of the
day and they just had like a whole bunch
of meetings they were stuck in traffic
for 5 hours they just got home they are
not they're absolutely not going to go
to the gym they're not going to eat a
healthy meal it's not going to happen
for them tonight and in this state if
they're opening your app and all that
they're seeing is that they didn't meet
their wellness and health goals like
they didn't make time to meditate they
weren't able to go to the gym their
calorie count or whatever is super low
if they know they're going to see this
they're not going to open your app and I
know that people have all sorts of
feelings about this they're like well
but they have to know the truth people
have to pick themselves up by their
bootstraps and like get to the gym even
if they had a really hard day but
they're not going to they're not going
to open your app and they're going to
churn right it doesn't mean that we
shouldn't give people accurate
information I'm just saying don't make
that the only thing your users see if
your goal is to retain them if somebody
just has a terrible night's sleep or had
a terribly stressful day how do you turn
that on its head and make it a
pleasurable experience and not as
shaming like oh you need to sleep better
you need you know stop stressing out so
much how do you flip those on their head
I don't
know honesty no seriously we don't have
quite the correct formula for it we made
a lot of mistakes along the way I'll
tell you the funniest thing we've ever
done as an app is you know the Rings in
people's Apple watch so we were like
okay these Rings great idea but like not
scientific enough they're not actually
adapting to users personally they're not
like scientifically tracking their
cardio they don't do cardio zones
correctly we'll make more scientific
rings and set smarter move goals for
people works really well for like a
small segment of the population but as
like retention driving cool feature you
know not that great because it has this
shaming effect so I don't quite know how
to solve this problem the way we solve
it right now is that we just try to
shift people's Focus to other things
along with like the bad metrics and
stuff that they see and we try to avoid
telling people what to do but this is a
big problem to solve and I don't want to
tell people that we know how to solve it
perfectly yet because to be honest I
don't I'm still still struggling with it
yeah but a good thing to be struggling
with I mean this whole conversation so I
started using Welter after meeting you
at Ma but I've been so busy and so
stressed and I'm like that typical user
but even this conversation is making me
want to dig in more so I wanted to shift
to something that you brought up when we
were talking about these kind of Loops
is that I compared this novelty and make
it pleasurable and stuff to do a lingo
and when I did that you were like no no
no like we've taken a very different
approach to Du lingo and I thought that
was really fascinating so I wanted to
like go a little bit more in depth about
what did you mean by that I kind of put
dualingo and I think people correctly
put language learning into the same kind
of category as apps that help you take
care of your health and wellness because
both of them have this really tough job
where they're trying to get people to
accomplish a long-term goal under
conditions where the shortterm task that
you have to do every day to get to the
long-term thing you're just like really
unlikely to do it it's hard we don't
have time we don't have energy and in
this sense like Welter and dual lingual
solving similar problems but we've taken
an entirely different approach and
there's a couple reasons for this one is
that with dual lingual and with language
learning in order to do a good job all
you have to do is open the app and spend
like 3 to 5 minutes in it just like
close your lesson get rewarded for it
immediately and there you go you're done
your language program for the day you
did a good job you didn't break your
streak and every time you do this you
get dual lingo just is really really
good at trying to shame you into opening
their app like for the entirety of the
day you know my favorite feature that
they have is I think they have this
either a gen Z or Millennial girl that
yells at you but like in a very
sarcastic way um
and then I also have the widget that
like shames you in different creative
ways like throughout the day so they're
really good at like trying to get you to
just open the up just open the up and
then once you're there all you have to
do is spend like a couple minutes
closing something you get rewarded for
it infinitely and they're coming up with
new ways to reward their users every
time like I think they recently added
this really Pleasant like buzzing
sensation when you do a really hard
question so even before you're done your
entire lesson you're already like
feeling those like pleasure dopamine
hits so they shame you and then they
just like reward you excessively for
every single move but they can do this
because with language learning you can
complete the task inside the app and you
can complete it quickly it's like you
can't get a better night's sleep in five
minutes in the grocery store line yeah
exactly so I think that's where a lot of
people that I talk to they kind of think
that someone is eventually going to make
the ideal like dualingo for health it's
going to give you like a little plan
that you can just do every day and that
it'll gradually get you to where you
need to be but that's much harder with
health because you can't do it in 3
minutes inside the app it has to be done
outside the app and it involves things
like sleeping for eight hours instead of
four and it doesn't make much sense yeah
so that's what I mean by that I think
that was one of the pivots that we did
we tried to give people these
personalized programs where they kind of
like do things during the day and then
they check off what they've done for the
reasons I already mentioned we chose not
to go that route and with language
learning you kind of have more
flexibility you can afford actually if
you make a really great product to have
tons of people just like churning and
like falling off the wagon because what
matters is you're still getting more
people than before to learn a new
language and that's really cool with our
app we really don't want people leaving
even if they're not doing anything even
if they can't stick to a plan we still
want them to be able to use our app and
to get value out of it even on days when
they're not able to do anything yeah
that's super cool and then I've heard
from tons of folks in the industry over
the last few years like as dual lingo
has risen to the level of success it has
so many people it's kind of like you
said want to create the dualingo of
Health and Wellness or create the
dualingo of productivity or whatever and
so hopefully thinking through these
things and thinking through that
contrast will help people better
contextualize what does and doesn't work
and maybe save them a few iterations on
their kind of reward cycle to not fall
into the Trap of thinking duelingo is
going to work in every scenario and then
those are some really key takeaways of
why duelingo works the way it does and
and understanding those things it's like
you see the loop in dualingo and I
hadn't done it before so this was super
insightful for me too of like having a
deeper understanding of why it works
then helps you apply it to your app in a
way that might actually work instead of
just copying and then falling flat and
wondering why it didn't work and then go
iterating through a bunch of Cycles to
figure it out so hopefully that helps
people I thought it was super
fascinating so next up I did want to
move to Innovation you y'all have done a
lot of innovative things in the app and
then you I know as VP of strategy it's
something you think a ton about day in
day out and working closely with the
product teams and kind of influencing
the product so how do you think about
innovation in the app and then lessons
that others can learn from to think
about innovation in their own apps I
really think that a lot of people have
the misconception of innovation being
spontaneous but in my experience
innovation has been basically a very
organized way of researching and
thinking about products and after a few
years I mean I've been at Welter for I
think seven years maybe even eight years
at this point and over the years I've
kind of developed an innovation
framework that our team uses to really
think through new features and I'm not
talking about monetization mechanics or
kind of small improvements but really
innovating new core features that
radically change your product and we've
used this framework successfully I will
say it's not perfect and I change it
every month or something like that but I
guess I can kind of explain how it works
and how to use it and maybe it can help
some people think through the new
features they're thinking about making I
think it will and another misconception
that I see a lot and we probably
perpetuate in some ways on the podcast
is that oh we'll just AB test our way to
Innovation we'll let the users decide
what's Innovative or not and and I think
that's kind of a trap too and again to
use du lingo as an example we had
somebody from dingo on the podcast I
think the title was something like why
to test everything or AB test all the
things but again it's like well you can
understand at dualingo why that works
they have a ton of resources and they
are doing Innovative things but they're
also a more mature company but I think
the trap a lot of folks fall into is
like oh we'll just test this oh we'll
just test this oh we'll just test this
without really truly innovating and
thinking through these things and then
what you're doing is you're just
spending a ton of resources on low
impact tests versus like building these
truly Innovative features that are going
to drive more attention more retention
and so yeah I think it's going to be
super helpful so yeah let's dig in and
the bigger problem with the AB testing
is not so much like I don't mind the
test everything approach of course you
have to test everything but um then
something works and because you hadn't
thought through it you don't know why it
worked or why it didn't work and that's
where the real problem actually is it's
it's not the testing everything it's why
did it work uh we don't know or though
especially for smaller more research
constrainted companies it's more the
opportunity costs of testing too many
low impact things instead of coming up
with things that could truly be more
impactful and then testing those
potentially more impactful things versus
just testing a million low impact things
I can talk you through some of the
pillars in our framework the first thing
that we always look out for is does the
thing that you want to make actually
align with the company Mission I think a
lot of people do this but a lot of
people also skip this part so ours is to
improve people's well-being with science
and technology that serve each
individual personally so if you're
making something that isn't geared
towards that we're not going to do it
like if it's things that are bad for
People's Health or aren't personalized
and don't adapt to each individual user
it probably doesn't make much sense for
us very simple but people skip this step
I've been thinking a ton about this
lately and at Revenue cat our mission is
to help Developers make more money and
it it's just been sinking in more and
more how much having a good mission
statement and then aligning everything
you do within the company to that
mission statement can impact the
trajectory of the business it was cheesy
at first to me but now it's like sinking
in more and more how important it is
that every single company meeting we
kick it off with whoever's leading the
meeting talking about our mission
statement and then talking through how
we're going to go about achieving that
mission and again it's like when we
first started doing it's like oh come on
like we all know the mission statement
whatever and then now like over like two
years it's finally sunk through my thick
head that when you start a meeting with
the mission statement we're going to
help developers make more money it
focuses the meeting it focuses the
products you build it's so important to
have some kind of aligning State even if
it's not a mission statement if you
think mission statements are cheesy or
whatever like just find something to
align to otherwise you're just going to
go a million different directions and
not have that Focus so 100% agree and I
think it's really cool this is like the
first step in your framework for
Innovation is like align with something
like have an idea of where you're going
and align with it so what's number two
number two is it's really a good idea to
visualize this person that you're trying
to make the feature for just know your
segments and know which one you're
making this particular feature for so
there are different types of people that
download health and wellness apps for
different reasons and like I said before
there's the athletes and the optimizers
there's a really funny segment that I
call Forever Young which is like these
people who just like want to look super
young and be super fit and like never
age they have a ton of money and a ton
of time but they're a very small
percentage of the population and then
there are people who are already sick or
people who have health anxiety like I'm
probably not dying but what if I am but
our biggest segment we personify him as
the dude from the big Labowski
uh I call this segment The Duda bides we
actually have ai generated images of the
dude and all sorts of like poses like
the dude at the office the dude after
work on the
couch and basically if we're making a
feature I try to think about how the
dude is going to respond to it it's
pretty funny but I just like to always
visualize our main segment you can make
things for other segments but just know
that most people like at most times in
the evening when they're opening apps
they're the dude all of us are the dude
at that point in
time that's such a great framing the
third thing we think about is what
triggers your covering so okay you have
your mission you have your key segment
that key segment what is happening in
their life that they've just opened your
app and are seeing your feature what is
the trigger that prompted them to be
like okay I'll open like dualingo or
I'll open Welter dualingo has an
artificial trigger they just have an owl
that chames you great trigger but you
know like when you open Uber it's
because you need to get somewhere and
like I said before with Wellness apps
the trigger is the main problem because
there's sometimes people want to just
you know like they just woke up they
think they had a really good night's
sleep and they want like a confirmation
of that in their sleep report or they
just downloaded your app and they're
really interested in exploring
everything in it and they want to see
how the data changes but you know a year
down the line that's not going to be a
trigger for them anymore and the trigger
that's most important for us like I said
is just boredom and existential horror
we want people to be seeing stuff in our
app when they're just bored in line at
the store or at home on the couch and
they're about to open Netflix but they
open us first instead that's kind of the
main trigger we try to work with I
really like thinking through that too
because if you build this awesome
feature in the app and there's no
trigger to go explore it nobody's going
to explore it so it's like you got to
think okay we've got this great idea
it's going to be this super Innovative
feature kind of like the Rings you were
talking about before and then you find
out oh well actually there's no like
trigger there so yeah that's a really
great step to Think Through in this
ideation and Innovation steps yeah
what's the next one the next one is what
job you're doing for the user and I know
that I said that there are no jobs to be
done in health and wellness Tech
before but what I meant by that is that
there are no jobs to be done because
there are no triggers and the only thing
you can do is like alleviate boredom
really on a day-to-day basis but if you
think more broadly like why people
download health and wellness apps to
begin with there are like high level
jobs there they're just not like
day-to-day jobs but people do have
certain expectations of things that they
want their Health app to do yeah like I
have a massive job to be done is have
more energy to play with my kids and
there's all sorts of those kind of
things that are those jobs to be done
but like you said it's like they're not
the jobs with Associated triggers I'm
not opening Welter because I'm thinking
oh I don't have much energy and then the
app's going to give me energy it's like
this yeah much more meta job to be done
yeah so we still think through jobs to
be done but with our app it's usually
meta jobs because the immediate jobs is
always just alleviate my boredom and
existential horror but they're also
highlevel jobs like people want this
ideal app that monitors and tracks their
health it gives them personalized
insights and recommendations it
facilitates Behavior change and helps
them feel better like you said it
educates them and then a lot of times
people want some kind of community or
social support I think that that is
important so you can think through
highlevel jobs like that like what do
people expect this app to do just
generally or you can go through and use
the classic jobs to be done framework
okay like you open the app for this
reason and what is the thing you need to
get from it right now both are important
the high level and the kind of like a
media level yeah so then how does that
start to play out in what features you
actually build and how you think about
Innovation we tried different ways to
kind of work with this framework one of
the dumbest things I tried to have
people do is for each of these like
completed triggers or segments covered
or stuff like that give like 10 points
and then if you're making a feature that
through the framework collects the most
points kind of like make that one first
you know eventually you need like a
system you want to try to quantify
everything but that's not the way
Innovation Works you can't just like
score every project with a framework and
expect to have the perfect backlog you
just have to think through the feature
and then use all of these standards to
try to figure out is it worth making and
if it is worth making like these are the
questions you need to ask yourself to
figure out what needs to be inside that
feature all right so you've aligned with
the mission you've figured out your
personas and Target segments you've
thought through what's going to trigger
folks to actually use this feature and
then you've thought through the meta and
individual jobs to be done for for that
feature what's the next step in
analyzing what to build and how to
innovate well for us like I said before
retention is super super important we
want people to never fall off the wagon
and to just keep coming back to us and
learning about the ways their bodies
work as a caveat retention is not always
important for all products I was using
an app to quit smoking and if you have a
high retention in an app that's helping
people quit smoking you're not doing
your job so maybe retention is not so
important for all apps but for us it's
really important so the next thing I try
to think through okay what is going to
be in this feature that helps it be a
driver of retention to our app and there
are I think seven retention drivers that
help create this for us so I think we've
gone through magic our wonderful anti-c
capitalist feminist concept we talked
about novelty so showing people
something new every time they open the
app another thing is relief so
again when people open your app are you
helping them alleviate that feeling of
boredom and existential horror are you
providing them with relief or are you
providing them with like shaming and
move goals or something like that
another retention driver is
personalization when people see
something that they know is relevant to
them personally and in the moment right
now they really love that obviously this
is something that folks know a lot about
but gamification if you can distract
people with a fun game when they open
your app like dualingo does great
retention driver it works a less obvious
one that I found to be very important is
bragging rights so duala actually does
this really well it gives you like a
little badge that you can put on your
social media whenever you do something
well so we make a lot of our content
sharable I have this really close friend
who really started sleeping better and
eating right and he was using wel tre's
magical fuel tanks and posting them on
his social media to kind of brag to
people like look my tank is blue today
because I'm super calm and that helps
people come back to your app more so
they can have more content from your app
to brag to their friends about and then
of course one that everyone knows about
is any kind of like social features that
help you engage with others straa does
this super well even on days where you
personally haven't gone for a run you
can go and spy like I don't know on your
like ex's run and laugh laugh about how
their pace is worse than it used to be
or something like that so social stuff
is a good retention driver so those are
the retention drivers and having these
written down to Think Through I think
will be really helpful for the audience
so we'll put a list in the show notes of
magic novelty relief personalization
gamification bragging rights social it's
a great L probably not exhaustive you
can probably come up with your own five
that maybe are more directly applicable
to your own app but again like just
great kind of structured thinking to
think through all these different
aspects as you're working on stuff so
then what's the next thing you think
about the next thing we think about this
probably should be the first thing I
think about but I'm not practical so the
other thing we like to think about okay
there are certain things that you must
do in your app people expect them and if
you don't have them they think it's
weird for example for a long time Welter
was an app where all of your sites and
guidance and Analysis is presented in a
feed format so you never know what's
going to like come up at the top and you
kind of have to scroll a lot of the time
to get to if you want to see your sleep
analysis you have to find it in your
feed it's not just like somewhere you
can recall it instantly and it works
super well but also people expect like a
home screen from a health and wellness
app that presents all of your stuff in
like different categories in an
organized way and if you are a health
and wellness app eventually you must do
this so features that are musts are
features that all of your competitors
have for example or say they fulfill a
promise that you sell people on like in
your ads or stuff like that if they help
fulfill that they're actually a must
feature and then features that if you
don't have them people will eventually
leave you for competitors and I think
the last one is users experience an
extreme level of frustration
if this is something that's not done
yeah and like fixing bugs and making the
app launch quickly and like there's
definitely some mus haves that do still
need to be prioritized and again even if
they're not Innovative you do have to
just get them done yeah exactly must are
weird sometimes you can complete Del
lighters before musts in order to like
win some users over you were saying that
you did this in your weather app
recently yeah yeah so the last category
on the list is delighters and we were
just talking about that how
in my weather app we have some musts we
have not done yet you know there's
expectations and we see it in the
reviews unfortunately we've gotten some
negative reviews of like how are you
charging $40 a year and you don't even
have this basic feature every other
weather app has but what we do have and
what we shipped and decided to
prioritize was a really delightful
widget experience and it was to the
point of this conversation it was a very
Innovative feature you know we packed
the better part of a weather app into an
interactive widget and so that widget
itself was super delightful and drove a
ton of acquisition and has driven
retention and people love it but now we
do need to kind of get back to some of
the musts that you know people are
justifiably pointing out that our app
doesn't have and this another I mean
just to side tangent for a little bit is
that in certain categories like weather
there's tons of people who actively
check two or three different weather
apps and so part of my decision making
in leaving those out was that people are
still going to probably check other
weather apps and so if I can create one
thing that's like so delightful that
they're willing to pay for my app even
if they have to go check those other
apps for other stuff they're still going
to come back to my app because that one
feature is so delightful and in my case
going to be right on their home screen
so yeah in my case I did prioritize that
delight and that Innovation over some of
the must haves but the cool thing for us
is like now that's kind of bought us
enough active users and enough active
subscribers and enough kind of Runway as
a side project to now go back and fill
in some of those must to complete some
of that experience especially as
competitors might eventually launch
these delightful widgets similar to what
we've done but yeah how else do you
think about delighters and then since
we've already done it contrasting like
how to prioritize Delight over musts
over retention drivers and then as you
said previously some features can be all
three the last category I try to think
about is this a delighter feature and
delighter feature I mean I know that
everyone talks about this and there's
really no way to know for sure if a
feature is going to Delight users like
you can guess and you can do your
research but basically the framework I
use is okay I think that every retention
driver is typically a delighter and that
delighters complete known jobs in a
particularly delightful way or they
create like some kind of like AA moment
or wow effect for users these are really
abstract Concepts I think my favorite
Delight lighter feature it's weird
because a lot of online a lot of people
complain about this but Netflix was the
first one to do an autoplay thing you
know you're sitting on the couch and
you've watched an episode and it
immediately starts playing the next
episode without you having to do
anything so that is both a retention
driver right because like you're going
to keep watching the TV show even if
you're like drifting off and it's also
like completing a known job in a very
particularly delightful it's also
magical cuz you do nothing and get
something for it one of my favorite
features of all time sometimes Del
lighters are like really dumb yeah well
funny enough I don't know if this was a
bug or if this was intentional or if
they fixed it but for a long time
Netflix would start the new episode but
do it in super low bandwidth and you
would actually have to stop and then go
out and go back in to get the high
bandwidth and my guess at the time was
that this was like the bean counters
looking at okay this is a really
delightful feature it's driving
retention but it's really expensive
because we autoplay in Full Resolution
every next episode I hadn't thought
about how delightful that autoplay was I
thought about how frustrating it was
when it broke and I hadn't thought of it
as a delightful feature until you
brought this up and then realizing that
like a ban counter took away that
delightful feature because it was
probably costing too much money so I'll
have to recheck I haven't been watching
as much Netflix lately and so I'll have
to recheck and see if that was maybe a
bug and they fixed it or if it really
was like them saying ah people are
asleep anyways we're gonna like break
this delightful feature just to save
money but that gets to like the tension
of all these things right it's like you
do have to balance like how delightful
it is versus how much does it cost you
to deliver and those kind of things it's
all in so much tension there's also a
trap with delighters so they made this
delightful feature but sometimes if you
make a really good delighter that's it
it's a must now for the industry right
and it stops being like your thing it
stops being a delighter for you
everyone's going to just copy it and
have it so yeah and then you break it
and it's like a
frustration any more thoughts on
delighters or the rest of this framework
as we wrap up yeah my last pillar of the
framework don't listen to anything I
say because I think that there's a
tendency in product management to really
stick to very strict rules and like
score everything and like try to really
reduce it down to a science but I think
that there's limitations to how
organized you can make your thinking and
I use this framework not as a rule book
but as kind of like start to get your
brain going and when you're analyzing
competitors like doing competitor
analysis to do it not in like a loot but
in a very organized way that helps you
reach conclusions faster it's not a
scorecard that's not how it works so
yeah basically add to it create your own
things don't listen to anything I say
probably two years from now I'll throw
out this whole thing anyway so yeah well
it's been so fun chatting with you this
is a hoot is so much fun but also I feel
like incredibly valuable to our
listeners but is there anything you
wanted to share as we wrapped up yeah I
guess I could just say that we just
released some new features to help
people manage sedentary stress it's a
really Innovative cool thing it's
available for Apple watch users we're
still doing it for you know other
fitness trackers it takes a bit of time
because the data is in different formats
but if you want to go check it out it's
really great our users seem to really
love it awesome yeah and I don't
typically think of the podcast as a
distribution channel that anybody will
get any additional downloads because of
a podcast episode you know this podcast
is way more about the lessons that folks
have learned from building the apps that
they work on or or working on the apps
but I would say this is an exception I
think a lot of our audience probably is
like Jane the founder of Welter have
maybe struggled with burnout I know I've
struggled with burnout off and on for 16
years since I started my company and had
four kids along the way go download the
app so many of you listening or product
Builders yourself some marketers and
other stuff so definitely share feedback
because I I think that can be super
valuable so definitely check out the app
I'm going to subscribe and start taking
it more seriously sedentary stress is
probably the biggest like limiting
factor in my health and productivity so
that new feature y'all just launched I
think is really going to hit home and
help me so yeah download the app thank
you it was super nice talking to
you thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private community
[Music]